{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Funding for this site was secured for Peter Norbeck, though it was supposed to originally be placed in the Needles region to honor Red Cloud and Lewis and Clark. After abandoning a similar commission at Stone Mountain venerating Stonewall Jackson and Robert E. Lee, Gutzon Borglum designed this monument in the Black Hills. For ten points, name this South Dakota monument featuring the faces of four presidents.",
      "answer": "Mount Rushmore"
    },
    {
      "question": "This group placed former king Norodom Sihanouk under house arrest after a break in their alliance. This group transformed a high school into the notorious torture center S-21. After overthrowing Lon Nol to take power, this group set the calendar to “Year Zero” and sought to create an agrarian society. The “killing fields” were operated by, for ten points, what communist organization led by Pol Pot that ruled Cambodia in the 1970s?",
      "answer": "Khmer Rouge"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man agreed to give up his yearly consulship as part of the Second Settlement. The Praetorian Guard was established by this ruler. This man, who gave himself the title of “First Citizen,” or “princeps,” came to power after outlasting the Second Triumvirate and winning the battle of Actium, forcing his rival Marc Antony to commit suicide. For ten points, name this first emperor of Rome.",
      "answer": [
        "Augustus Caesar or Octavian",
        "Gaius Julius Caesar Augustus",
        "Gaius Octavius Thurinus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A golfer from this country is the only winner of the Masters to not have his jacket stored at Augusta, after he claimed to forget to bring it back; that golfer from this country became the first non-American to win a career Grand Slam in 1968. One of the earliest non-European golf clubs was founded in this country’s city of Durban. Gary Player is a golfer from this country who controversially supported Hendrik Verwoerd [feh-vert], though he later disavowed him. For ten points, name this country where the Cape Town Open is held.",
      "answer": "South Africa"
    },
    {
      "question": "A cartoon satirizing this meeting shows three men on the edge of a cliff and is partly titled LEAP NO LEAP. Delegates known as “Blue Lights” attended this meeting, which was presided over by George Cabot. A debate in Pennsylvania’s senate opposed this meeting’s proposal to overturn the Three-Fifths Compromise. This meeting was portrayed as treasonous by Democratic-Republicans. For ten points, name this 1815 meeting of New England Federalists.",
      "answer": "Hartford Convention"
    },
    {
      "question": "The leader of this organization sent a message reading “Wait for my call” and a knife emoji to his wife shortly before she reported him missing to French authorities. Kim Jong Yang became the leader of this organization after Meng Hongwei, its first Chinese president, resigned after he was detained on bribery allegations by Chinese authorities in October 2018. For ten points, name this international agency that coordinates crimefighting efforts between nations.",
      "answer": "Interpol or International Criminal Police Organization"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1887, this device was the agreed upon solution to the problem that the Gerry Commission tried to resolve. Dentist Albert Southwick was inspired to invent this object after an incident involving a drunken man. Often employed at Sing Sing, this device was used in 1953 on a couple found to have leaked nuclear program secrets to the Soviets. For ten points, name this device used to execute the Rosenbergs, that relies on sending a current through the victim’s body.",
      "answer": "electric chair"
    },
    {
      "question": "This government renounced its claims over the Baltic States after it was forced to sign the Treaty of Rapallo. This government’s parliament was torched by Marinus van der Lubbe, leading to a crackdown on civil liberties in a series of Fire Decrees. Thanks to heavy debt from the War Guilt Clause, this government faced hyperinflation of the deutschemark. For ten points, name this German republic that was established following World War I.",
      "answer": "Weimar Republic"
    },
    {
      "question": "A new religious movement from this country worships “God the Parent” and teaches about achieving the “Joyous Life.” Along with that religion, Tenrikyo, another new religious movement in this country became recognized as a terrorist group after it released sarin gas in a subway. A controversial shrine in this country honors war criminals, and many other shrines in this country honor spirits or deities called “kami.” For ten points, name this East Asian country home to Shintoism.",
      "answer": [
        "Japan or Nippon",
        "or Nihon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "After manning a machine gun during this event, Dorie Miller became the first African-American to receive a Navy Cross. A perpetrator of this event was apprehended in the Niihau incident by civilians. This event was carried out in two waves by Vals and Zeroes, who sunk the Arizona. President Roosevelt lamented “a date that will live in infamy” in a speech to Congress after, for ten points, what surprise attack that brought America into World War II?",
      "answer": "attack on Pearl Harbor"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s son Fu Su was forced to commit suicide over his support for general Meng Tian. Under the advice of chancellor Li Si, this man implemented increasingly Legalist policies. This man burned the books of Confucian scholars and buried them alive to eliminate dissent. To prepare for the afterlife, this man adorned his tomb with thousands of terracotta warriors. For ten points, name this first emperor of a unified China.",
        "answer": [
          "Qin Shi Huangdi",
          "Ying Zheng",
          "Zhao Zheng",
          "King Zheng of Qin"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Qin Shi Huangdi oversaw the construction of one of these engineering projects known as Lingqu. A “Grand” one of these projects connects Beijing and Hangzhou.",
        "answer": "canals"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A speech by this man notes “Fondly do we hope, fervently do we pray, that this mighty scourge of war may speedily pass away.” In that speech, this man advocated for a policy of “malice toward none with charity for all.” This man noted that a “government by the people... will not perish from this earth” in a speech that began “Four score and seven years ago...” For ten points, name this President who delivered the Gettysburg Address.",
        "answer": "Abraham Lincoln"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The quote “malice towards none with charity for all” derives from this Lincoln speech, delivered near the end of the Civil War.",
        "answer": "Lincoln’s second inaugural address"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle’s result was investigated by the Catroux Commission, which reported that its greatest effect was upon public morale. Charles Piroth committed suicide after discovering he could do no more in this battle, whose sides fought to control hills codenamed Beatrice and Gabrielle. During this battle, artillery pieces placed in the mountains were used by great effect by Vo Nguyen Giap, who had surrounded his European enemy. For ten points, name this 1954 battle that led France to withdraw from Vietnam.",
        "answer": "Battle of Dien Bien Phu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The result at Dien Bien Phu significantly altered the proceedings at a 1954 conference held in this Swiss city. A set of Conventions signed in this city discuss the rights of civilians and prisoners of war.",
        "answer": "Geneva Conference and/or Conventions"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Maria Reiche’s studies of these works has led her to be nicknamed “the Lady” of them. Drone research has led historians to conclude that these works were inspired by similar ones created by the Paracas Culture. An Adler Planetarium astronomer claimed that these works were created for the purpose of pointing out “heavenly shapes.” Created roughly 2,000 years ago, these works were made by the removal of dark sand to expose lighter colored soil below. Animals like jaguars and llamas are depicted in, for ten points, what natural artworks created in ancient Peru?",
        "answer": "Nazca Lines"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A theory about the creation of the Nazca Lines involves a medieval version of this object to observe the designs. The Montgolfier brothers famously designed one of these objects.",
        "answer": "hot-air balloon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During a siege of this city, a prisoner was freed after he held his hand in a fire without injury. During another siege, this city was betrayed by a woman who was crushed by shields before being thrown from the Tarpeian rock. Those sieges were carried out by Lars Porsenna and Titus Tatius, the latter being a king of the Sabines. The early history of this city was described in Livy’s Ab Urbe Condita. For ten points, name this city legendarily founded by Romulus and Remus.",
        "answer": "Rome"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lars Porsenna was a king of Clusium, a city founded by these people. This civilization dominated northern Italy until its conquest by Rome in the 4th Century BC.",
        "answer": "Etruscans"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A policeman complained “I have just bought some new furniture” when he was suspended from his job in 1963 after the revelation that he had arrested this author years earlier. This author, who called herself a “bundle of contradictions,” addressed her work to a character she created named “Kitty.” For ten points, name this author who died in Bergen-Belsen concentration camp after writing a diary in hiding.",
        "answer": "Annelise Mary “Anne” Frank"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Anne Frank’s family hid in a house on the Prinsengracht canal in a series of rooms known by this name, which was also the original title of Anne’s diary when it was first published.",
        "answer": "the Secret Annex or Het Achterhuis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ship’s passengers became the subject of a charity fund operated by James Pennington. Shortly after Joseph Cinque seized control of this ship, it was captured off of Long Island by the Washington. This ship, owned by Ramon Ferrer, had been redirected from Cuba to New York, triggering an 1841 Supreme Court case that ruled that this ship’s Mende captives were free. For ten points, name this Spanish ship that was taken over by a slave revolt.",
        "answer": "La Amistad"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This lawyer and former President argued on behalf of the Africans on board the Amistad before the Supreme Court in 1841.",
        "answer": "John Quincy Adams"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The Space Race",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "US government agency responsible for the administration of the space program.",
          "answer": "NASA or National Aeronautics and Space Administration"
        },
        {
          "question": "First artificial Earth satellite, launched in 1957 by the Soviet Union.",
          "answer": "Sputnik 1"
        },
        {
          "question": "First man in space, who entered orbit in the Vostok 1 in 1961.",
          "answer": "Yuri Alekseyevich Gagarin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dog plucked off the streets of Moscow who became the first animal to orbit the Earth in 1957.",
          "answer": "Laika"
        },
        {
          "question": "American mission whose three-man crew was lost to a cabin fire in 1967.",
          "answer": "Apollo 1"
        },
        {
          "question": "First American man in space; he later hit golf balls on the Moon.",
          "answer": "Alan Shepard"
        },
        {
          "question": "First space station operated by the United States; it orbited Earth from 1973 to 1979.",
          "answer": "Skylab"
        },
        {
          "question": "African-American mathematician who verified the computer’s orbital trajectories for John Glenn’s first orbit on Glenn’s request.",
          "answer": [
            "Katherine Johnson",
            "Katherine Coleman"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "French Revolution",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "French King beheaded in 1793 along with his wife, Marie Antoinette.",
          "answer": "Louis XVI"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prison that was stormed in 1789, marking the beginning of the French Revolution.",
          "answer": "Bastille Saint-Antoine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary who was executed in July 1794 after growing the Committee of Public Safety during the Reign of Terror.",
          "answer": "Maximilien Robespierre"
        },
        {
          "question": "French aristocrat and officer who fought in the American Revolution before joining in the French Revolution.",
          "answer": "Marquis de Lafayette"
        },
        {
          "question": "Vow taken by members of the Third Estate in 1789, formally establishing their opposition to the ruling monarch.",
          "answer": "Tennis Court Oath"
        },
        {
          "question": "French finance minister whose dismissal from the service of the king incited a major rebellion in 1789.",
          "answer": "Jacques Necker"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary figure executed for the assassination of Jacobin leader Jean-Paul Marat.",
          "answer": "Charlotte Corday"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Revolutionary calendar month in which it occurred.",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country she led as Prime Minister.",
          "answer": "India"
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of Indira Gandhi, the first Prime Minister of their country.",
          "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru"
        },
        {
          "question": "Military operation that Gandhi authorized in Smiling Buddha; American examples took place at Bikini Atoll.",
          "answer": [
            "nuclear weapons test",
            "equivalents"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion followed by the bodyguards who assassinated her in 1984.",
          "answer": "Sikhism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Holy site in Amritsar where she ordered a deadly raid, enraging those bodyguards.",
          "answer": "Golden Temple of Amritsar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name for the 21-month period in the mid-70s when Gandhi suspended elections and violated civil liberties.",
          "answer": "The Emergency"
        },
        {
          "question": "Medical procedure forced on millions of people during that time period, meant to curb population growth.",
          "answer": [
            "forced sterilization",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Period of agricultural change, championed by Norman Borlaug, that Gandhi fostered during the fourth Five Year Plan.",
          "answer": "Green Revolution"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one work, this man called for a “radical revolution of values” after claiming “[his] conscience leaves [him] no other choice.” Another of this man’s works noted how “no lie can live forever.” This orator of the “How Long, (20 pts)",
        "Not Long” speech claimed that a group has been given a “check which has come back marked insufficient funds” after predicting an “invigorating autumn of (10 pts)",
        "freedom and equality.” In that speech, this man hopes his four children will be “judged not by the color of their skin but by the content of their character.” For ten points, name this civil rights activist who gave the “I Have a Dream” speech."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.",
        "MLK"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This institution was based on the earlier katorga system, and its growth turned Magadan into an industrial city. This institution was praised in the report Solovki by Maxim Gorky. This system was compared to an (20 pts)",
        "archipelago in an Alexander Solzhenitsyn novel that brought it to the public’s attention. NKVD-led kangaroo (10 pts)",
        "trials led political opponents to be sent to these locations. For ten points, name this system of forced labor camps set up in Siberia under Joseph Stalin."
      ],
      "answer": "gulag system"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Michelle Alexander argued that these institutions perpetuate a racial underclass in her book The New Jim Crow. Jeremy Bentham designed a type of these institutions that Foucault later discussed in a book subtitled for “The (20 pts)",
        "Birth of” them. A subject nicknamed “John Wayne” was one person whose abuses led Philip Zimbardo’s (10 pts)",
        "experiment simulating these institutions to end after only 6 days. A 1971 Stanford University experiment replicated, for ten points, what type of facility where criminals are incarcerated? ANSWER:prisons(orjails;orcorrection(s)centers/facilities;orpenitentiaries;promptondescriptive answers relating to the justice system in the first sentence) (4) This man adopted the Plan of Cuernavaca and the Seven Laws, though he dissolved Congress afterwards regardless. This man was removed from power by the Plan of Ayutla after serving (+) 11 non-consecutive terms. During the Pastry War against the French, this man was struck by a cannon at (*) Veracruz and had his amputated leg buried with full military honors. For ten points, name this Mexican general who failed to thwart the Texan Revolution, despite leading forces at the Alamo."
      ],
      "answer": "Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A shopkeeper named Consider Tiffany wrote about this man’s capture. William Hull popularized a quote given by this man, who was most famous for an action that occurred simultaneously with one group’s escape to Morningside (20 pts)",
        "Heights. This man was caught a day after the Great Fire of New York following the Battle of Long Island, in which he was tasked with providing (10 pts)",
        "information on the British. For ten points, name this Revolutionary War spy who said “I only regret that I have but one life to lose for my country.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Nathan Hale"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of these things inspired and names the second and most famous symphonic poem in Bedrich Smetana’s collection Ma vlast, known as “The Moldau” or “Vltava.” The spacecraft docking scene in (20 pts)",
        "2001: A Space Odyssey was set to a piece of music named for one of these things. Handel’s Water Music was commissioned to be played while King George II (10 pts)",
        "traveled along one of these features. For ten points, name this type of geographic feature that inspired Johann Strauss’ waltz “On the Beautiful Blue Danube.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "rivers",
        "Danube River after “spacecraft” is read",
        "Thames River after “Handel” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man seized the Stone of Destiny after his troops deposed John Balliol at the battle of Dunbar. While leading troops for his father, this man was captured at Lewes but later escaped and defeated the rebellious (20 pts)",
        "Simon de Montfort at the Battle of Evesham. After succeeding (10 pts)",
        "Henry III as king, this man defeated the rebellion of William Wallace to become known as the “hammer of the Scots.” For ten points, name this English king who was nicknamed for his great height."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Edward I",
        "Edward Longshanks"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The central figure of this event was ordered to recite the Seven Penitential Psalms weekly for three years. Robert Bellarmine was a primary antagonist of the target of this event, which occurred several decades after a similar incident resulted in the (20 pts)",
        "execution of Giordano Bruno. Publications like The Starry Messenger were condemned as part of this event, whose target was sentenced to (10 pts)",
        "house arrest in 1633. For ten points, name this event which forced an Italian to recant his heliocentric claims."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "trial of Galileo Galilei",
        "descriptive equivalents"
      ]
    }
  ]
}